NIKUDAN
(THE HUMAN BULLET)
SECOND DAWN INN
LIFE EXPECTANCY IN JAPAN
IN 1945: MEN: 46.9
IN 1967: MEN: 68.5
WOMEN: 49.6
WOMEN: 72.3
Why do women live longer?
Well, that doesn't matter.
Without war, the human
lifespan is very different.
Let's try to subtract.
This is terrific.
A difference of 21. 6 years.
21 years... Wait a minute...
That's surprising.
What a coincidence.
No, it fits too well to be a coincidence.
But it's true.
A t the time, he was...
21 years and six months old.
I' m 21 years and six months old now.
This is the end.
You look healthy.
But it's all over for you.
This year, will it be Iwo Jima?
Or perhaps Okinawa?
That's what the lady on the beach said.
It's true.
They even captured Okinawa.
Everything is over.
It's as embarrassing as
someone seeing your belly button.
Therefore, it's all over.
What do you think,
ain't it great to be alive?
Actually, you and I are
the only living creatures here.
So let's be friends!
By the way, did you see anything in there?
Really?
You can't see anything in my stomach?
Yeah, true.
The bomb that fell
on Hiroshima is a new kind.
Well, according to
the section commanding officer...
Boom! Everything is over!
Will Okinawa end up blown away?
Kyushu will be next.
It's all over.
And it's a good thing that it's all over.
Exactly like someone saw our belly buttons.
It's so shameful.
Set fire!
Back then, he never felt shameful.
He wouldn't even blush.
Did everyone get their flints back?
If you forgot your flint
at the bomb site, raise your hand!
You again!
Spread your legs!
Take off your glasses!
Clench your teeth!
Get up, cadet!
Report your name!
Yes Sir!
Special first-class ground officer cadet
of the pioneer section of land forces,
third squadron of the third division
of the third army, Sakura Taizaku.
Cadet Sakura!
Tell me why you broke
into the food warehouse
during your night watch,
and stole four bags of hardtack?
It was three bags.
Speak up!
I remember that my stomach was empty.
Oh, your stomach was empty?
They were eating rats in Guadalcanal!
Give me more details! Why?
That's sort of a long story.
Tell me why!
We cadets changed ourselves into cows.
Cows?
You mean the ones that go "moo," with horns?
Exactly.
All the cadets started to ruminate.
Wait! What is ruminating?
Ruminating means to regurgitate the food
you've swallowed, and then chew it again.
A ruminant animal is one who
repeats the operation, such as the cow.
Wait, is that kind of thing
technically even possible?
If you train a little, it's possible.
I don't believe you.
Show me how!
- I'll repeat!
- Permission to repeat!
That was just the hardtack from before.
I don't feel well.
Are you even human?
I am a cow.
I want to become human again.
It may not be a good time,
but may I offer my advice?
Your advice...
Okay, speak!
Cadet Sakura at your command!
All the cadets are suffering from hunger.
Two thirds of the rear are malnourished.
One third is sick in bed.
One third is absent from training.
The last third goes to the infirmary.
If I may talk about myself...
I used to weigh 58 kg before enlistment,
and now, after about half a year,
I've dropped off to 42.5 kg.
The only reason...
The only reason is the
clumsy chewing skills of the cadets!
It's not the army's wages!
The wages and rations are enough!
As the Company Chief declared
during the last company dinner:
Chew 48 times!
When you chew 48 times,
every meal you see appears
to be your own dish of meat.
I will now give you an example.
Start eating!
But two thirds are malnourished,
one third is sick in bed,
one third is absent, one third...
Enough!
What's your point?
This warehouse.
What about it?
There's plenty of food!
These are provisions for the final battle!
The cadets won't
make it to the final battle!
What?
Think about New Guinea! Imphal!
Attu, Leyte, Guam, Saipan!
We all thought about
Iwo Jima and Okinawa in vain.
What the heck?
What the heck are you trying to tell me?
I'm starving.
No! I don't care about your stomach!
I want to hear what you think
about Iwo Jima and Okinawa!
Iwo Jima!
Okinawa!
Then Kyushu, and it'll be over.
So, you want to escape?
No, I don't.
There's no escape except to fight.
Japan is an island nation. I'll fight!
But I can't fight on an empty stomach!
Yes you can!
You only need the spirit to
face hardship and deprivation.
You were all incorporated
as Corporals this New Year's.
In April you'll be Sergeants.
In August, you'll undergo the Second
Lieutenant Accelerated Formation Program.
Therefore you must give up Sundays,
holidays, and meeting with civilians.
Sure, the meals probably
aren't enough for a growing man,
but the whole point of this
is to increase your ability
to face hardship and
deprivation very quickly.
The other cadets supported this training.
But you don't support it...
Pig!
- Pig?
- Yes, you're just a pig.
The pig is a symbol of poor character.
That's right, pigs are naked.
You!
Get naked!
Naked?
Yeah. Until special order,
you're forbidden to wear the vest,
trousers, jacket, overcoat, undershirt,
loincloth, socks, boots, or gaiters. Repeat!
Until special order,
Cadet Sakura will not wear the vest,
trousers, jacket,
overcoat, undershirt, socks...
Wait!
You forgot the loincloth!
I won't wear the loincloth,
boots, socks, or gaiters.
Good! Begin!
Um...
What?
What about the glasses?
What's your degree?
It's 0.02 and 0.06.
Keep your glasses.
But a pig wearing glasses...
Isn't it inappropriate?
Who cares?
There are one or two pigs
with intellectual faces.
Anyway, you'll be with cows.
If there's one pig wearing glasses
among the cows, it doesn't really matter.
It doesn't matter.
It really doesn't matter.
The cows showed a little bit of
gratitude towards the pig,
because the herd had
increased by a little bit.
So they had a little bit of respect for him.
For example, listen to their compliments...
Hey, his dick is pretty big, ain't it?
It doesn 't matter.
No, it really doesn 't.
He didn 't catch a cold.
He was cured of his allergies.
Judging by his face,
he had no time to catch a cold.
It doesn 't matter.
No, it really doesn 't.
Until the special order...
And while he was thinking
the special order would never come...
A new kind of bomb was dropped on Hiroshima.
The USSR declared war.
The new bomb was also dropped on Nagasaki.
The special order finally came.
Sir Academy Principal,
it's sinister to shed tears before departure.
Please say something.
What is there to say...
This place once belonged to the
probationary low-officer of the army.
But that's a story of the past.
In short, they're preparing
to dismiss the troops.
Starting today, you, the special first-class
cadet ground officers of the third period,
will go to the final battle
as His Majesty's Holy Shield,
as an anti-tank special unit.
Starting today,
you're no longer humans, but gods.
I wish you continued luck in the
fortunes of war, and a good fight.
That's all.
That's all...
Indeed, that really was all.
A man who became a cow, then a pig.
Instead of returning to human form,
he rose to the level of a god.
That's the whole story.
"Is there anything worse than
standing before a crying man?"
That's from a kamikaze pilot's last letter.
He probably also felt that way.
He would certainly prefer
to be a man instead of a god.
To wish you good luck for
your departure, let's have a toast.
Cheers!
It doesn 't feel so bad to be a god.
Piles of seafood and delicacies,
and a lot of sacred wine.
Do it firmly.
Commander, will we do it together?
Of course, let's die together.
"Really?" He thought.
"Well I don 't really care about that. "
"What I really care about
is how to spend my day today. "
"We cadets are getting our first
day off since we entered the army. "
"So we only care about spending
our free time in the best way. "
"We don 't know about the rest.
Only the gods know. "
"Wait a minute! I'm a god too! "
"I'm a god, but I have no idea. "
"Indeed, I've just been promoted. "
"Anyway, let's go. "
It doesn 't matter.
This doesn 't matter either.
This white-haired old man
is old enough to retire.
That's all.
Since he 's retiring,
he 's getting a pension.
But instead of money,
he 's being paid with goods.
That's all.
Three bales of rice,
three bags of flour,
three bags of beans,
three bags of sugar,
and a truck.
That's all meaningless.
Whether he makes money from transporting
cargo or selling sweet red-bean soup,
it doesn 't really matter at his old age.
This kind of life also exists.
That's the whole story.
SECON DHAN D BOOKS
Is this all?
Yes, that's all, private.
Do you have a thicker one?
One with lots of pages
that I could use as a pillow?
I sure do, private.
You do? Please show me.
The phone book, private.
I don't want the phone book.
It's not interesting.
Something more interesting...
But not too interesting.
Something I won't finish in two days.
Something fairly interesting,
but also fairly boring.
Something I can read every day.
I don't know how many days I'll need it.
I've got one.
How about the Holy Book, private?
Holy Book?
You mean... the Bible?
Yes, the Bible.
It's hard to read sometimes,
but it's fairly interesting.
Where is it?
Ah, this will make a good pillow.
How much is it?
It's free, private.
- Free?
- Yes, free.
But could I ask you for
a small favor in exchange?
Sure, what is it?
I have no hands.
They were taken by a B-29.
My arms were ripped from my shoulders.
I usually ask my wife,
but unfortunately she's out shopping.
I've been desperately
waiting for someone to come.
Oh, I get it, you need to pee?
Exactly!
Well that's okay.
I haven't laughed so hard for a long time.
Neither have I,
but now I need to go even worse!
Okay, let's go.
Where is it?
Over there.
It feels so good, private.
Really? Glad to hear it.
You must not die.
If you die, you won't
be able to enjoy this anymore.
That's right, but...
Wow, it lasts so long.
It never seems to stop.
Yes, maybe there's something wrong.
There's nothing wrong.
Everything looks fine.
I guess so.
I trust you would know better than my wife.
Thanks.
Private, what are you...
Ah, it finally stopped.
What are you doing later today?
Whoring around, because I only have
one day to spend as a human being.
Whoring around? How nice!
Really?
It's your first time, isn't it?
You're right.
How did you know?
I can tell because your face
has a look of impatience and anxiety.
Oh, yeah?
You're probably right.
My feet and hands are itchy.
Exactly.
I must have been like you back then.
Maybe I was, but that's an old story now.
It goes back to the
end of the Russo-Japanese War.
It's a very old story.
But private, let me just tell you this:
The first time is very important.
You'll either enter Heaven,
or descend to Hell.
How was it?
Like falling headlong.
The shock was so big!
Desolate. I was very desolate indeed.
That girl was as scary as a Deva King.
Although they all
look like the Goddess of Mercy.
Darling...
Yes?
Is he a customer?
Yes, he helped me with that daily thing.
He did?
Thank you so very much.
She's exactly like the Goddess of Mercy!
True. That's the reason
I've lived up until now.
Thank you.
Where the hell are you going?
Ah, I'm going to the brothel.
Where is it?
The brothel?
You bastard! It's the first time
someone has asked me that.
It's my first time as well.
Anyway, today is my first and last day off.
Okay, I'll tell you.
Wait a second.
What's that book?
Is it a foreign book?
It's the Holy Book in Japanese.
The "Horny Book? "
Bastard. Is it your first time for that too?
Huh? Yeah.
It isn't like what's in the manuals.
It's like war. You charge with a
human bullet and let the enemy deal with it.
The enemy who looks
like the Goddess of Mercy?
Goddess of Mercy?
Certainly not!
They're nothing but freaks!
I guess your first time was no good...
What?
I mean, you're telling me
that the first time is important, right?
Exactly! Go for it!
Ah, could you just tell me how to get there?
NEW DEVELOPMENT
- Come here, baby!
- Freak!
What a freak!
What a cutie!
A freak!
Help! Let me go!
They're all freaks!
Hey you! Come over here!
SECOND DAWN INN
The Goddess of Mercy!
It really is her.
What?
Is that factoring?
Yes, but I can't understand this part.
Do you?
Ah, maybe.
Let's try.
Equals A squared plus two AB...
Plus C, bracket...
Bracket A squared,
plus B squared, plus C squared,
minus BC, minus CA, minus AB, bracket.
That's it!
Um... Is this also a...
Yes.
How much?
For soldiers, four yen and fifty sen.
May I?
Yes, please.
Here.
What's this?
You'll understand soon.
Here's some tea.
Oh, thank you.
Um, money?
I'd like to have the money now.
Please, it's the custom.
Four yen and fifty sen is too much.
It's fine. Money is meant to be spent.
That's what I think.
You could buy another algebra book.
Thank you very much.
Sorry, all the blankets have been burned.
The pillows too.
Wait a minute.
You're... pretty.
"All the blankets have been burned."
"The pillows too."
"Therefore shall a man leave
his father and his mother,"
"and shall cleave unto his wife,
and they shall be one flesh."
"And they were both naked,
Adam and his wife, and were not ashamed."
I see...
Oh boy, a soldier!
I love soldiers!
What's going on?
You're in the wrong room, Ma'am.
Don't call me Ma'am.
This room is for that girl
with the pigtails and school uniform.
School uniform?
No, she's the landlady.
- Landlady?
- Yes.
The boss and his wife
were both killed in an air raid.
The miss now runs the place by herself.
Her only brother died in the war.
She's so brave.
So even though I'm an old bag,
you should just deal with it.
It's all the same anyways.
Really? That's great!
But Ma'am, your apron...
Oh, I was peeling potatoes.
Don't worry about it.
Desolation. This is true desolation.
If you had to picture desolation, it's this.
A freak with an apron.
An apron... can't be a woman!
A white-collared apron
and a mole below the knee...
That can't be a woman!
A soldier with an umbrella.
That can't be a soldier!
I'm a sergeant, a cadet.
You cadets only borrowed
the grade of sergeant, unlike us.
You're just second-class soldiers inside.
What the fuck is that umbrella for?
It's because of the rain...
Bullshit!
The chinks are the only
soldiers in the world with umbrellas.
When will you wankers be promoted?
Next month,
on the first of September.
Japan is doomed if all the
sublieutenants are so textbook like you.
We haven't lost yet.
True, we haven't lost.
I just mean that even if we're winning,
we'll lose if we're led by wankers like you.
I'm not gonna lead anyone.
I'll blow myself up near an enemy M4 tank.
Oh, suicide squad?
The suicide squad are gods!
So you should act like a god
and not use an umbrella.
I'll be a god tomorrow.
Today I'm a human.
That's why I want to hold an umbrella
under the rain like a human.
Can't you forgive such a little thing?
Sure, I forgive you.
Since I forgive you, only use your
umbrella when you get out of my sight.
Well, it would be faster if you
just turned and looked away.
Okay. Like this?
Yes. Bye!
Hey!
Honey!
Darling!
Hiromi!
Here's tobacco...
Rice...
Bean paste...
And this too...
A cubed plus B cubed plus C cubed...
minus three, times ABC...
Equals bracket...
A plus B plus C plus...
bracket, bracket, bracket...
Excuse me.
Thank you.
Is it that?
- Yes, that...
- Okay.
That again...
Bracket A squared plus
B squared plus C squared...
Minus, minus, minus...
Minus BC minus C minus AB...
Bracket, bracket, bracket, bracket...
That's it!
Why?
Where are you going?
A couple and their child died here.
They were smothered like wax dolls.
Your...
My dad, mom, and five year old sister.
And you?
I've been working at a factory.
There's a blanket behind you.
It's dangerous to be wet like you.
You are too.
Can I have it?
Were you born in the year of the rooster?
No.
Why?
You're thin like a rooster.
Year of the rat.
21 years and six months.
I was year of the rabbit.
Rabbit, rabbit...
What did you see that made you jump?
What did the rabbit see that made him jump?
Yes, Mr. Rat?
Yes!
Well... err...
I forgot.
That's naughty.
It was the 15th evening's moon
I saw it and jumped
Bravo!
That's what dying is...
You don't see anything.
You don't hear anything.
Your brother who died at the front,
was he in the army or the navy?
Where did you hear that?
The old lady with the apron.
Old lady?
He was in the army,
but he died on a ship like in the navy.
It was a ship of veneer, for one person.
Like a motorboat?
I see...
In the army, we call it the SS Boat.
The bow is full of explosives,
and it crashes into enemy boats.
A boat for one person must be lonely.
You too?
No.
I'll be alone, carrying explosives
towards the enemy tanks.
I'll dig a foxhole, hide in there,
and wait until the enemy tanks arrive.
With a box of explosives on my shoulders,
I'll run under the enemy tank.
The M4 is pretty solid.
But the metal plate at
the bottom is its weak point.
It doesn't work with a Caterpillar.
If you're underneath it,
it's impossible to run away.
But I'll probably lose my mind by then.
I'll be mindless, but fearless.
I'll wait for days and days in my foxhole.
I'll see the M4 coming!
Closer and closer...
I'll go crazier and crazier.
The M4 is coming!
20 meters, 15 meters, 10 meters...
Now's the time!
Where are you going?
Am I pretty?
Yes.
Very.
Mr. Rat, it's me, Rabbit.
Where are you?
- Private Rabbit, attention!
- Yes, Sir!
- One step forward!
- Turn to the left!
- Yes, Sir!
- Two steps forward!
- Turn to the right!
- Yes, Sir!
- Three steps forward!
The enemy! Duck!
I could die for this!
I could die for you!
I could die to protect you!
Japan is a beautiful country all year long.
Its mountains, rivers,
and oceans make it a beautiful country.
We were born in this great country.
Our fathers and mothers
were also born in this country.
Our grandfathers and grandmothers
were born in this country as well.
Japan is a great country, a pure country.
The only country of the gods in the world.
Japan is a good country, a strong country.
A glorious country that enlightens the world.
Mr. Soldier, are you dead?
Not yet...
But it's as painful as dying.
Then you should go in the sea.
That will relax you.
Really?
It's true.
It feels so good.
Careful! It's a bomb!
Hey, are you alright?
I shouldn't have frightened you.
I wanted to be serious,
but I was careless. Sorry.
Then... is this a fake?
Yes.
The real ones are yellow,
and have some really powerful gunpowder.
But I won't get one until tomorrow,
so I'm practicing with this.
What's inside?
Sand.
Come on!
Hey Mister, are you
guarding this coast all by yourself?
All this by myself?
That's impossible!
I'm not that strong.
How many people then?
Well, just a few.
Wait a second...
You won't tell anyone?
Don't worry, I'm Japanese.
The walls have ears and the doors have eyes.
We're surrounded by spies.
Okay, Okay.
There's almost a hundred of us.
Digging holes and hiding in them.
That's so cool.
So we'll be safe even if
they come with a hundred tanks.
Well, apparently there
should be about that many.
You're so cool, Mister!
No I'm not. I'm normal.
I'm just normal and nothing else.
No, you're great.
You're a human bullet.
Human bullets are great, Mister!
You think so?
Yeah, Mister.
Cut it out with the "Mister!"
I'm still young.
Just call me "bro."
But you've got hair on your legs.
So you're an adult.
You're right.
Do you have a brother?
Yeah. No dad or mom, but a brother.
He's working at a factory in the city.
This world has seen
the rise and fall of many countries.
There was the Greek Empire.
There was the Roman Empire.
Hey, that's his voice.
In China, there was the Han, Tang, and Yuan.
Weird, he's supposed to be in the city.
Many countries that
were prosperous, then fell.
It really is him!
For thousands of years, there have been
heroes who sacrificed
their lives fighting for their country.
Hey, he's talking about you!
But these heroes disappeared
as soon as their country vanished.
They couldn 't even save their
names when the country vanished.
Japan isn't gonna vanish!
The natural mountains and rivers
didn 't change during this time.
When spring came, the plants still grew.
Brother!
But the people were left with a different
native country than their ancestors had.
From ancient times up until today,
there's been only one country that has
stayed the same, and that is great Japan.
Before the beginning of history,
before history was even a word,
Japan was already the country of the gods.
Ever since Izanagi and Izanami
gave birth to the country,
the great Japan has developed
into a flourishing country.
Now, Japan is fighting against America,
England, and many other countries.
Since December 8, 1942, with the
wise declaration of His Majesty the Emperor,
all of the imperial subjects,
obeying His Majesty's will,
have devoted themselves
to His Greatness with passion.
The Pacific Ocean and the South Seas
have given birth to a new Japan,
just like the Eight Islands
were born in the age of the gods.
This legend has been passed on forever.
As His Majesty the Emperor Jimmu
and His Majesty the Emperor Meiji wished,
the day has come when we may enjoy the
brightness of His Majesty the Emperor Showa.
So we must all do our best
to create a brand new history.
Whoever writes and teaches
these manuals must be crazy.
Got it, you bad student?
Yes, but there's a part I don't understand.
What? Where?
Well Izanagi and Izanami is
such an old story, so I can't tell...
But are the Pacific and South Seas
really the cradle of a new country,
or just some extra pieces?
Bastard!
Who the hell are you?
And you?
- I'm a teacher.
- Just as I thought.
Crazy.
What?
That's not the point.
Why did you hit him?
This little punk ran away from the factory!
Is that true? Why?
I was worried about my brother.
Yeah...
These two boys were left
alone in the world. Can't be helped.
But the factory makes
bullets for machine guns...
Isn't it too late for that?
So why did you hit him?
But it's for the Pacific, the South Seas...
Japan is lost.
We're not building a new country,
just protecting the one we have.
So why did you hit him?
Look, all this blood...
I know...
How much money do you have?
Just a little.
Thanks. For the medical fees.
Look at all that blood.
This should be enough.
Thanks. See ya.
Oh, hurry up and make some bullets.
Are you gonna fight with your bamboo stick?
No... bullets.
Watch out!
There are landmines everywhere!
Everyone's going crazy.
I know I acted like a gangster,
but that's all they understand.
Hurry and see a doctor,
so you don't go deaf.
Thank you.
You're so awesome, Mister!
No I'm not. I'm normal.
My school grades were
even a little below average.
But you defeated the teacher just by talking.
Isn't that above average?
Yeah, maybe. See ya.
Mister! Are there really landmines?
I'll plant them tomorrow,
so keep out after that.
Well, take care you two.
Take care! Goodbye!
ADVANCED COURSE OF
MORAL TRAINING FOR BOYS VOL. 3
That day, he was summoned by his father,
who was a junior high school principal.
Also present was his mother,
who wasn 't much older than he was.
The strict father and the sensual mother.
His father entrusted him with a six-shooter
that belonged to his warrior
ancestors of the Bakumatsu Period.
Die, my son.
Die as the Emperor's Shield.
Let us meet at the Yasukuni Shrine.
His mother squeezed out a tear,
and she squeezed a pimple at the same time.
He bowed, stood up, and started to walk,
then tripped over the border and fell down.
Stop! Thief!
Ma'am! That's dangerous!
Ma'am! That's really dangerous!
Is your pistol broken?
No, my grandfather used it
at 203 Hill during the Russo-Japanese war,
so it should be alright.
Because we're still using the same
kind of bullets in the Type 38 rifle.
But the bullets got wet.
That thing's a hundred years old.
They're a little wet,
but it should still work.
You really frightened me.
What happened to you?
What happened to me?
I should ask what happened to you!
Nothing to be proud of, really...
It's a long story.
Is that okay?
Yes. I have plenty of time.
Really?
Soldier, it's all over.
Yeah.
Probably.
They even captured Okinawa.
It's all over.
It's as embarrassing as
someone seeing your belly button.
Actually, I cook for a group of fishermen.
This afternoon, they said there was
an order to evacuate women and children.
That's it, isn't it?
Doesn't that mean the
Americans will arrive soon?
Ah, who knows?
Doesn't it?
They said that the Americans would
crush the balls of the Japanese men.
Really?
How will they do that?
And what will we do without them?
That doesn't really matter.
They said that the Americans would
take all the Japanese women as mistresses.
Oh.
That's what they said.
I'm horrified just thinking about it.
So you wanted to die?
Yes, but even if I threw myself in the sea,
I'm just too good at swimming.
And there are no trees
to hang myself, just sand.
Then I fell in that hole.
Really?
But you shouldn't die.
When you're alive, even a little thing
like going to the bathroom is enjoyable.
I suppose so.
Well, now that you mention it...
Bracket, X squared
plus X minus 12, bracket...
Plus 24 equals...
Ah, that's it!
If I make X squared plus X equal to Y...
Bracket Y minus 12, bracket,
Y minus two, bracket, plus 24 equals...
Y squared minus 14 Y plus 48...
Equals bracket, bracket...
Mr. Rat, do you think I'm pretty?
Yes, very.
You're a very cute rabbit.
Rabbit, rabbit,
What did you see that made you jump?
What was it?
The 15th evening... no...
14 Y plus 48 equals... um...
Equals bracket Y minus six,
bracket, bracket Y minus eight...
Equals, equals, equals...
Bracket minus two, bracket...
X squared plus X minus six, bracket...
That's it!
- Aristotle?
- Or Socrates?
Which one?
He's exactly the same.
I remember. It's that philosopher
who lived in a barrel in the sunshine.
- Greek?
- Wasn't he Roman?
The king asked him, "How can I help? "
And he replied, "Don't disturb me."
What is he thinking with those glasses?
Doesn't look like anything important.
- About what to eat or do.
- Or women.
- But he's a god.
- A weird god.
The Divine Spectacled Mole God.
- Let's ask for a favor.
- Seduce him?
We shall kneel before him.
Can he control himself?
It's okay. He's erect.
On the verge of explosion!
- Who, you?
- No, the Lord of Glasses.
- Shall we?
- Let's do it!
- I'm first!
- No, all together.
Alright. All together.
Let's sink this ship!
Get out, Nimitz and MacArthur!
After you get out,
you can go straight to Hell!
- Is this the Jirocho family raid?
- The Divine Bamboo Stick Gods.
Can you kill with a bamboo stick?
Looks more painful than a bayonet.
- Are they soldiers too?
- Looks like a training school.
They're fishermen's sons.
- What shall we do?
- There's too many.
- I thought we'd be alone.
- Japan is an island nation.
- There are too many people.
- It's for the final battle.
- Forward, hundred million fireballs!
- I wish it were night.
- I wanna swim!
- Me too.
To wash away our transient lives.
- We Nightingales won't die.
- What about our virtue?
- Bite your tongue.
- But before biting,
we'll cut off the part
that's hostile to women.
- The ideal Japanese woman.
- Sada Abe.
- Well I wish it were night.
- Which way is it?
We don't know east from west.
Let's ask the Divine Spectacled Mole God.
Yes, I completely forgot about him.
Mr. Mole, which way should we go?
We just arrived today.
Please tell us.
To the Defense Headquarters.
The lady in trousers who attempted suicide
was in the kitchen at the Headquarters.
She gave him some rice balls and miso soup.
M ister!
Hey!
What's up?
I'm going back to
the factory with my friends.
Even if that teacher's there?
I have no choice.
My friends are waiting.
Oh yeah?
- Your brother too?
- Yes.
It's safer if I take him too.
Mister, this is for you.
What is it?
Sweet potatoes.
They're boiled, so cut and dry them.
Thanks, but what about you?
Don't worry.
Our bags are full of potatoes.
Then I can't refuse.
Thank you!
Is there anything we could do for you,
like send a message to a friend in town?
Send a message...
- Would you do that for me?
- Of course!
Do you know the Kanamachi
New Development on the outskirts?
Isn't it the entertainment district?
You know? Yes, that place.
The factory is there,
so I often go there pulling a wagon.
That's great. There's a place there
called Second Dawn Inn.
Second...
Dawn Inn.
- Second Dawn Inn.
- Yes.
There's a girl who looks like the Goddess
of Mercy, in pigtails and a school uniform.
The Goddess of Mercy...
A schoolgirl?
Yes.
Tell her Rat says "hello."
Rat, Rat, Rat... Is that you, Mister?
Yes.
Just, "hello."
I'm counting on you.
Second Dawn Inn, a schoolgirl
who looks like the Goddess of Mercy,
Rat says, "hello."
That's right.
Who is this girl to you, Mister?
Well, you could say she's my fiancé.
"Fiancé? " That sounds like "pickles."
When the war ends,
if we're both alive, I'll marry her.
Awesome! The Goddess of Mercy and a rat!
Let's go. Bye.
Bye. You take care.
If there's an air raid,
you should be the first in a shelter.
Second Dawn Inn, right?
- Second Dawn...
- Goddess of Mercy and Rat...
A long time ago, in the land of Izumo,
there was a wise and merciful god
known as the Great Lord of the Land.
The Great Lord of the Land
was the youngest of his many siblings.
Since he was very nice,
he would always carry his brothers' things
whenever they went somewhere together.
One day, he put all his
brothers' things in a big bag,
and carried it while following them.
Since it was so heavy,
he kept lagging behind his brothers.
In the land of Inaba,
they reached a shore called Keta Cape.
There on the beach was a bare red
rabbit whose fur had been ripped off.
He was crying from the pain.
With compassion, the Great Lord asked,
"Poor Rabbit, why are you in such bad shape? "
The rabbit told him
the following story, in tears...
It's the sharks!
It's the rabbits!
The three white rabbits of Inaba.
Our objective is the enemy ahead!
Charge!
The Divine Bamboo Stick Gods caught
the Divine Princesses of the Red Cross.
It was like a very old story to them.
It seemed like that
nearly nine-thousand-year-old myth.
Probably because the moonlight made
the beach look like the desert of the moon.
Then the sharks,
who were probably drunk, stripped the
fur off the rabbits until they were bare.
Hey ho! Hey ho!
Those are B-29s!
80, no, 90 of them!
The town!
The town is under attack!
Rabbit! Hang on!
Don't die! Rabbit!
Don't give up! Don't die!
Mister!
What happened?
Everyone died!
My brother, the Goddess of Mercy, everyone!
This is all that's left.
Bracket X squared plus X minus 12,
bracket, bracket, bracket...
I'll get revenge!
My brother died like a baked potato!
Bracket X squared plus X minus 2,
bracket, bracket, bracket...
The Goddess of Mercy girl
was smothered like a wax doll!
Bracket plus 24 equals, equals, equals...
Hey! Let's avenge them!
Bracket Y minus 12, bracket,
Y minus two, bracket, plus, plus, plus...
Plus X minus eight, bracket, equals bracket
X plus three, bracket, bracket X minus two...
Bracket X squared
plus X minus eight, bracket...
That's it!
Idiots!
How will we get revenge?
I picked this up.
Picked it up?
I stole it.
What will you do with it?
You take the tanks,
I'll take the machine guns.
- Human bullets?
- Yes, human bullets!
Japan is a beautiful country all year long.
Its mountains, rivers,
and oceans make it a beautiful country.
We were born in this great country.
I'm afraid this country isn't so great.
The war made a big mess of it.
Our fathers and mothers
were also born in this country.
Our grandfathers and grandmothers
were born in this country as well.
We were born at the worst time.
Japan is a great country, a pure country.
The only country of the gods in the world.
Japan is a good country, a strong country.
A glorious country that enlightens the world.
It's better to be pure than dirty.
A country of people is
better than a country of gods.
Is it a strong country now?
A glorious country that enlightens the world?
How nice.
I wish it was like that.
What about now?
It's hopeless right now.
A country where kids like you
have grenades is hopeless.
I'll keep it until the enemy arrives.
It's dangerous.
If it were a great country,
kids would be studying.
I was actually studying too.
You were a university student?
Yes.
But I was a bad student.
I should have studied more.
That's all that's left in my heart.
There won't be anything left
if you run into a tank.
But if you don't study,
you'll be a roly-poly or
stinkbug when you're reborn.
I don't wanna be a roly-poly.
Then you should study,
so you can become a human again.
There are lots of sad things about
being human, but lots of fun things too.
I don't want to be a roly-poly either.
I'll study!
The train fare is six sen per person.
How much is it for nine people?
Six nine, six nine...
54!
How much is it for ten people?
Six ten... 60!
The students are told to sit in their chairs.
There are six chairs.
If four students sit on each chair,
there are six students left.
How many students are there?
Hey Mister, how do you do this one?
Cadet Sakura!
The war plan has changed!
We have information that
enemy troops are heading north.
We shall advance and beat them!
Advance... in the sea?
Yes, you will beat them in the sea!
The SS Boat suicide squad base
is ten kilometers east on the coast.
Get your instructions there.
Yes! I'll repeat!
Don't repeat! It's too urgent.
Be independent and run!
Yes!
- However...
- What?
Don't run away.
You couldn't if you tried.
Some cadets ran away during the air raid,
but they were arrested this morning.
They were shot for the crime of desertion.
One...
Two...
Three...
Four...
Five...
Six...
Seven!
If these are 15 yen each,
how much does that make?
Yes! Seven times five is...
Seven, five... 35!
Seven times one is... Seven...
Seven... Well...
Um...
What? You want an SS Boat?
There isn't even a scrap left.
What are they telling you now?
The enemy got to Kyushu
and apparently just left.
There's nothing to panic about.
But there's new information.
The enemy is heading north.
Exactly. That's why the army panicked
and moved along to the next navy base.
They have Mosquito Dragon midget subs there.
What? What are those?
There's a whole bunch of Type 93 torpedos,
but the enemy has radar and planes,
so we can't use them the regular way.
- Have you ever seen a torpedo?
- No, never.
Then I'll tell you about them.
It might be useful for you.
It is 5.75 meters long.
It weighs one ton.
The diameter is, well... 45 centimeters.
It has about 200 kilograms of explosives.
It can travel at 42 knots for two kilometers.
Isn't that amazing?
How do you use it?
I have no idea.
I've only been assigned as a messenger.
Maybe you straddle it
and crash yourself into the enemy.
Like that.
Oh, well, stand up!
Turn to the left!
The Mosquito Dragon base
is ten kilometers east.
Run!
Why would they kill all these young men?
We should just end this pointless resistance.
It really makes me sick...
Well, that explains why he
ended up floating out here, all alone.
The suicide squad has many evocative names:
Divine Wind, Return to Heaven,
Sea Quake, Cherry Blossom...
But from his birth to this very moment,
he was just a nobody without a name.
If you had to give him one,
"Exploding Tortoise " might be appropriate.
There wasn 't really anything he could do.
A destroyer dropped him off here
where the enemy is supposed to come.
But would the enemy really come?
That was the problem.
Suppose he 's lucky and the enemy comes.
He 'll use his hands to paddle towards them.
He 'll untie the rope, pull the lever,
pray to make a hit, and shout three "banzai. "
Then there 's another problem.
The destroyer said they
would pick him up afterwards.
Oh really?
Because he 's in trouble
if nobody picks him up.
Nobody knows where he might
drift in the Kuroshio current.
Which way does it go?
The South Pole?
The North Pole?
Well, that doesn 't matter.
What matters is the enemy.
If they come, there 's nothing to worry about.
He was given rations for three days.
But he had a feeling he 'd
need to keep them for at least a week.
Well, it all depends
on the enemy or his allies.
Because he didn 't know when the enemy would
come or when his allies would pick him up.
Suicide squad!
Divine Wind!
Good luck! Good luck!
The bastard's ignoring me!
Go on! Go on and beat them!
It's a Grumman!
I don't wanna be a roly-poly.
Three times three is nine.
Three times four is 12.
Three times five is 15.
Three times six is 18.
Three times seven is 21.
Three times eight is... twenty... twenty...
I don't wanna be a roly-poly! Ah, 24.
Three times nine is twenty... twenty...
Twenty... twenty... twenty...
Hey old lady!
You're in the way!
Take that!
What?
You're in the way.
I can't see the enemy.
The enemy isn't coming.
Our troops have withdrawn.
Huh?
Why'd they do that?
Japan... Japan has...
Japan has lost.
No way! Japan is a good, strong country!
The only country of the gods in the world!
There are no gods or Buddhas.
Just now...
There was a broadcast from the Emperor.
I didn't understand all the big words,
but he said we've all done our best,
and we have to stop the war.
I won't stop!
But you have to.
It's an order from His Majesty.
I just saw a bunch of soldiers
throwing away guns, bullets,
and swords like it was merely firewood.
Oh yeah, they said it was
an unconditional surrender.
When I saw them throwing
all that stuff away, I started crying.
I felt abandoned.
Don't cry!
I don't care if I become
a roly-poly! I'll fight!
I'd rather be a roly-poly!
THE EMPEROR HAS ENDED THE WAR!
RETURN TO YOUR ORIGINAL UNITS!
FIGHT! THIS IS THE AUTUMN OF
THE FINAL SACRIFICE OF 100,000,000!
I don't care if I can't see.
I just care about the enemy!
Since that plane comes so often,
the enemy must be nearby.
If I can't see, I'll make them come to me!
My objective is a large aircraft carrier!
Rabbit was killed,
that kid's brother was killed,
and my meal was destroyed,
all because of those planes!
I'll get them!
The old couple at the bookstore...
The lady in the apron...
The lady in the trousers...
The kid with the grenades...
I must protect them all!
Rabbit, rabbit,
What did you see that made you jump?
It was the 15th evening's moon
I saw it and jumped
Attention!
One step forward!
Turn to the left!
Two steps forward!
Turn to the right!
Three steps forward!
The enemy! Duck!
The sun...
Looks like a big red pickled plum...
Pickled plum... Pickled plum...
The sun...
The sun rises in the East...
It's wrong! The enemy is
in the opposite direction!
A large aircraft carrier!
The enemy aircraft carrier
is approaching from behind-right!
It's coming closer!
Change the aim!
It's approaching fast!
Hurry, the distance is 600!
Aim is okay!
The enemy stopped!
Don't get excited... Calm down...
The distance is about 100.
The aim is okay.
No, go a little backwards.
Good...
The aim is good!
Good, now let's check!
Depth gauge is good!
Lever is good!
Now untie the ropes!
Good luck...
Now go!
Idiot! What are you doing?
What the hell?
Hey!
What are you doing here?
Stinks...
Did you drift here?
No, actually I'm from the suicide squad.
Suicide squad?
You must've had a rough time.
Had a rough time? First of all,
it's dangerous for you to be out here!
What do you mean?
We're just outside Tokyo Bay.
The authorities want me
to go much farther out.
Tokyo Bay?
I left from Enshu-nada,
about ten nautical miles away.
Really? Then you've drifted pretty far.
But at least the war is over.
Over?
The war is over?
When? Is it true?
Sure, didn't you know?
About ten days ago.
Ten days?
But just yesterday they told me
the enemy was heading north.
No way, you just must be really tired.
So you've been asleep
in there the whole time.
Oh, of course.
Please come aboard.
It's pretty smelly, but nevermind that.
Thanks, but could I have some water please?
I apparently haven't had any for ten days.
Sorry, but I don't have
any water, just "explosive."
Explosive?
Yeah, homemade shochu.
Want some?
Yes, even "explosive" would be okay.
Oh yeah?
You should come up onto the
boat to drink, so you can lay down.
No, I've been upright this whole time.
If I lay down too fast, I might die
from going horizontal so suddenly.
Oh, I see!
Yeah, you might be right.
Sorry to ask this,
but would you pull me to Tokyo?
Yeah, sure.
Since your life was just saved,
you should toast by yourself.
Here.
Thanks.
It's over.
The war is over.
Go, hey!
The goddamn war is over!
Rabbit! Japan has lost!
Bracket, XY squared plus 2A,
bracket, bracket, bracket...
Just like that!
The aim is good!
Fire!
Fire what?
Equals, equals, equals...
Rabbit plus Rat equals zero!
Rabbit and I are zero!
Trousers, apron, and bookstore are zero!
They're all zero!
Japan is a good country, a pure country.
The only country of the gods in the world?
Rabbit!
Fifteenth evening!
You idiots!
Rat, you idiot!
Rabbit, you idiot!
Idiots! Idiots! Idiots!
THE SUMMER OF 1968
Rabbit! Fifteenth evening! Rat, you idiot!
Rabbit, you idiot!
Idiots! Idiots! Idiots!
Written and Directed by Kihachi OKAMOTO
Producer: Kazuo BABA
Cinematography and Lighting: Hiroshi MURAI
Production Design: Iwao AKUNE
Music: Masaru SATO
STARRING:
Minori TERADA
Naoko OTANI
Yunosuke ITO
Shoichi OZAWA
Kunie TANAKA
Subtitles by maifeng,
motakutou, and tubesoda for ADC
Please don't sell copies of this fansub!
Narrator: Tatsuya NAKADAI
THE END